International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers, Industrial Aircraft Lodge 1746 Records 1983.0005
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers, Industrial Aircraft Lodge 1746 Records
undated, 1943-1983
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1983.0005
49 Linear Feet
The International Aircraft Lodge 1746 was chartered on 1 November 1945. The local represents production workers at United Technologies Corporation's Pratt and Whitney plant in East Hartford, Connecticut. The workers make jet engines and other components for commercial and military aircraft. Lodge 1746 is a member of IAMAW District 91.
History
The International Aircraft Lodge 1746 was chartered on 1 November 1945. The local represents production workers at United Technologies Corporation's Pratt and Whitney plant in East Hartford, Connecticut. The workers make jet engines and other components for commercial and military aircraft. Lodge 1746 is a member of IAMAW District 91.
Arrangement
The International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers, Industrial Aircraft Lodge 1746 records are arranged in the following series:
Series I: Administrative Records (undated, 1945-1983) is arranged in seven sub-series. By-Laws includes the by-laws of IAMAW Lodge 1746 and the Machinists Club from 1946 to 1980. Minutes includes the minutes of Executive Board meetings from 1955 to 1961, of Membership meetings from 1955 to 1961 and 1969 to 1970, of the Meriden Plant from 1960 to 1961, and announcements of local meetings from 1960 to 1979. Correspondence includes incoming and outgoing correspondence of the president from 1953 to 1954, 1971 to 1972, 1976 to 1977, and 1981; general correspondence from 1950 to 1979; and correspondence from other lodges from 1961 to 1979. Election material includes rules and ballots from 1968 to 1978, results from 1961 to 1976, officers rosters from 1945 to 1979, and letters of acceptance from 1970 to 1978. Subject Files includes correspondence financial records and reports of the Lodge 1746 Building Association, of District 91, and of the Grand Lodge; and correspondence with the Connecticut State Council of Machinists, the Connecticut State Labor Council, the Greater Hartford Labor Council, and Pratt & Whitney. This material is arranged alphabetically by name. Conference Materials includes proceedings of the Guided Missile Conference from 1957 to 1959, the Aircraft Missile and Related Electronics Conference of 1961, and the IAM Aerospace Conference from 1974 to 1975; and correspondence, minutes and proceedings of the New England Conference of the International Association of Machinists from 1958 to 1975. 1960 Strike Records includes general information pertaining to the participation of IAMAW Lodge 1746 in the 1960 strike with Pratt & Whitney.
Series II: Contracts and Negotiations (1946-1982) is arranged in two sub-series. Negotiations includes correspondence pertaining to contract negotiations from 1950 to 1966 and minutes of the negotiating committee for 1960. Contracts includes contracts between Pratt & Whitney and the local unions for plants in East Hartford, Meriden, Portland, Rockville, and Manchester from 1952 to 1982. These materials are arranged chronologically.
Series III: Financial Records (1943-1979) contains financial reports and correspondence of the Finance Committee, arranged alphabetically by type.
Series IV: Membership Material (1957-1980) contains check-off lists from 1960 to 1979 (with gaps); minutes of the membership committee from 1957 to 1965; records of per-capita payments to District 91 from 1975 to 1980; and membership reports from 1958 to 1961 and 1975 to 1977. These materials are arranged alphabetically by type except for the membership reports, which are located at the end because of their size.
Series V: Employee Information (undated, 1962-1980) is arranged in two sub-series. General Employee Information includes statistical data on employee distribution and wages and information on lay-offs, seniority, and transfers, all arranged alphabetically by type. Employee Service Records includes employee information from 1964-1980, arranged chronologically. The employee service records are computer-printed listings of active employees, provided monthly by the company to the union as stipulated by the union contract. They are listed alphabetically by name of employee, by clock number, or by department number. The records provide important data on the production workforce, including race, sex, employment and promotion dates, pay grades, etc. The more recent years also note union membership. Archives staff took a one month sample per year. Officers of Lodge 1746 requested that the Archives take a June sample, as it represented average union membership (their contract provides for a "drop-out" period in late fall, when employees may remove themselves from union membership). Use of materials in Series V.B Employee Service Records is partially restricted. Researchers may access the information in the series for statistical, trends and similarly broad purposes but no personally identifiable data provided in these files is to be associated with any findings.
Series VI: Job Descriptions (circa 1952-1980) contains standard forms describing machinist job qualifications and responsibilities at the Pratt & Whitney plant, and general information and correspondence pertaining to job evaluations and job presentations.
Series VII: Printed Material and Memorabilia (undated, 1955-1980) is arranged in two sub-series. Printed Material includes publications of the AFL-CIO, IAMAW Lodge 1746, Machinists Non-Partisan Political League, and Pratt & Whitney. Material is arranged alphabetically by creating body except for the IAMAW Lodge 1746 flyers, which are boxed separately because of their size. Memorabilia includes buttons, ribbons, photographs, and certificates pertaining to the activities of Lodge 1746.
Restrictions on Access
Restrictions on all materials has expired with the exception of grievance, arbitration and case files. These files are restricted from use by all researchers except with permission of the President of the local.
Use of materials in Series V.B Employee Service Records is partially restricted. Researchers may access the information in the series for statistical, trends and similarly broad purposes but no personally identifiable data provided in these files is to be associated with any findings.
Acquisition Information
The records were deposited by William Rudis, President of the local, 22 November 1983.
Civil law; Courts; Manchester (Conn.); Actions and defenses; Arbitration, Industrial; Labor union meetings; Machinists; Rockville (Conn.); Aerospace industries; Portland (inhabited place); Job descriptions; Publications (documents); Photographs; Connecticut (state); Press releases; Correspondence; Notebooks; Financial Records; Administrative records; Hartford (inhabited place); Political participation; Periodicals; Resolutions (administrative records); New England (general region); Photocopies; Meriden (inhabited place); Congresses and conventions; Notes; East Hartford (Conn.); Aircraft industry; Employees; Labor unions; Aircraft industry workers; Strikes and lockouts; Blueprints (reprographic copies).
- Series I: Administrative Records, undated, 1945-1983
  - Subseries A: By-Laws, 1946-1980
    - Lodge 1746, 1946-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
    - Machinists Club, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Subseries B: Minutes, 1955-1979
    - Executive Board, 1955-1961 (Box 1, Folder 8-12)
    - Membership, 1955-1961, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 13-19)
    - Meriden Plant, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
    - Announcements, 1960-1969, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 22-32)
  - Subseries C: Correspondence, 1950-1981
    - President's, 1950-1960, 1971-1981 (Box 1, Folder 33-38)
    - General, 1950-1968 (Box 1, Folder 39-44)
    - General, 1969-1979 (Box 2, Folder 45-48)
    - Ladies Auxiliary, 1962-1967 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Membership, 1960-1978 (Box 2, Folder 50-51)
    - Other lodges, 1961-1979 (Box 2, Folder 52-60)
  - Subseries D: Election Material, undated, 1945-1979
    - Acceptance letters, undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Excusal letters, 1965-1979 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Officers roster, 1945-1979 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Results, 1961-1976 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Rules and ballots, 1968-1978 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Subseries E: Subject Files, undated, 1950-1983
    - AMVETS, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Atomic Energy Commission, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Benefits, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 68-76)
    - Building Association
      - Bylaws, ca. 1953 (Box 2, Folder 77)
      - Correspondence and reports, 1952-1963 (Box 2, Folder 78)
      - Financial records, 1952-1963 (Box 2, Folder 79-84)
      - Building design and construction, ca. 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 85-89)
      - Building design and construction, ca. 1953-1955 (Box 3, Folder 90-93)
    - Bureau of Labor Statistics, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - Bureau of National Affairs, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Committees, 1957-1982 (Box 3, Folder 96-108)
    - Conference of American Small Business Organs., 1966 (Box 3, Folder 109)
    - CT Consumer Association, undated (Box 3, Folder 110)
    - CT State Council of Machinists, 1960-1966, 1970-1979 (Box 3, Folder 111-116)
    - CT State Labor Council, 1961-1979 (Box 3, Folder 117-122)
    - District 91
      - Bylaws, 1957-1964 (Box 3, Folder 123-124)
      - IAMAW Retirement Club bylaws, undated (Box 3, Folder 125)
      - Executive Board minutes, 1960-1965 (Box 3, Folder 126-131)
      - Executive Board minutes, 1966, 1971-1979 (Box 4, Folder 132-141)
      - Correspondence, 1960-1979 (Box 4, Folder 142-146)
      - Election results, ca. 1970s (Box 4, Folder 147)
      - Financial records, 1960-1961, 1974-1979 (Box 4, Folder 148-149)
    - Donation requests: general, 1960-1979 (Box 4, Folder 150-155)
    - East Hartford Aircraft Federal Credit Union Bylaws, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 156)
    - Government officials: correspondence, 1961-1978 (Box 4, Folder 157-159)
    - Grand Lodge, IAMAW
      - Highlights of IAM History, ca. 1973 (Box 4, Folder 160)
      - General correspondence, 1954-1976 (Box 4, Folder 161-168)
      - General correspondence, 1977-1980 (Box 5, Folder 169-170)
      - Audit reports, 1963-1970 (Box 5, Folder 171-172)
      - Circulars, 1957-1978 (Box 5, Folder 173-174)
      - Contract, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 175)
      - Election material, 1968-1974 (Box 5, Folder 176)
      - IAM scholarship program, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 177)
      - IAM special schools, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 178)
      - IAMAW-UAW separation, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 179)
      - Landrum-Griffin bill, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 180)
      - Pamphlets, 1958-1960 (Box 5, Folder 181)
      - Receipts and disbursements, 1961-1978 (Box 5, Folder 182)
      - Reports, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 183)
      - Walker, Elmer: correspondence, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 184)
    - Greater Hartford Labor Council, 1966-1977 (Box 5, Folder 185-186)
    - Hotel Restaurant Employees Local No. 59, 1976-1979 (Box 5, Folder 187)
    - Human Services Coalition, 1979-1981 (Box 5, Folder 188)
    - Insurance, 1964-1978 (Box 5, Folder 189-195)
    - Lay-off and reallocation, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 196)
    - Machinists Non-Partisan Political League, 1958-1979 (Box 5, Folder 197-200)
    - Pratt & Whitney
      - Booklet: "Pratt & Whitney - A CT Employer", 1983 (Box 5, Folder 201)
      - Blueprint of plant, undated (Box 5, Folder 202)
      - General correspondence, 1950-1978 (Box 5, Folder 203-206)
      - Morse, N.B., undated (Box 6)
        - Correspondence, 1961-1972 (Box 6, Folder 207-210)
        - Meetings, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 211)
      - News & Notes, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 212)
      - Notices, 1976-1979 (Box 7, Folder 213)
      - Salary rates, undated (Box 7, Folder 214)
      - Supervisor's Employee Relations Manual, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 215)
      - Wage and policy and practice, 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 216)
    - Stewards, 1957-1981 (Box 7, Folder 217-236)
  - Subseries F: Conference Materials, 1957-1975
    - Aircraft, Missile and Related Electronics Conference, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 237)
    - Guided Missile Conference, 1957-1959 (Box 7, Folder 238)
    - IAM Aerospace Conference, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 239-241)
    - New England Conference, IAM, 1958-1975 (Box 7, Folder 242-248)
  - Subseries G: 1960 Strike Records, undated, 1960
    - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 249-252)
    - General Information, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 253-254)
    - Medical services, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 255)
    - Strike duty, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 256-257)
    - Strike list, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 258)
    - Strike relief-disbursements, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 259)
    - Strike settlement agreement, undated (Box 7, Folder 260)
    - Supplement list, undated (Box 7, Folder 261)
- Series II: Contracts and Negotiations, undated, 1946-1982
  - Subseries A: Negotiations, 1946-1966
    - Check off agreement, 1946-1948 (Box 8, Folder 262)
    - 1950 contract: correspondence (Box 8, Folder 263)
    - 1953 contract (Box 8, Folder 264)
    - General correspondence, 1958, 1960-1966 (Box 8, Folder 265-268)
    - Interpretation of contract, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 269)
    - Minutes negotiation committee, 1957-1960 (Box 8, Folder 270-272)
    - Photographs: contact negotiations, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 273)
  - Subseries B: Contracts, 1950-1982
    - Meriden, 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 274-275)
    - East Hartford, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 276)
    - Supplemental agreement to 1950 contract, 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 277)
    - East Hartford, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 278)
    - East Hartford, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 279)
    - Meriden/Portland, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 280)
    - Meriden/Portland, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 281)
    - East Hartford: wage reopener, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 282)
    - Meriden/Portland: wage reopener, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 283)
    - East Hartford, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 284-285)
    - Meriden/Portland, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 286)
    - Rockville, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 287-288)
    - All plants, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 289)
    - East Hartford, supplemental agreement, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 290)
    - Meriden, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 291)
    - Manchester, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 292)
    - Meriden, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 293)
    - East Hartford, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 294-296)
    - Manchester, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 297)
    - Meriden, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 298)
    - All plants, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 299)
    - Proposals, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 300)
    - East Hartford, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 301)
    - Manchester, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 302)
    - East Hartford, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 303)
    - East Hartford, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 304)
    - Proposals, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 305)
    - Power Systems Division, Pratt & Whitney, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 306)
    - Printed contracts, 1968-1982 (Box 8, Folder 307-308)
- Series III: Financial Records, 1943-1979
  - Annual reports, 1957-1959 (Box 9, Folder 309)
  - Arbitration expenses, 1971-1978 (Box 9, Folder 310-316)
  - Audits, 1946-1961 (Box 9, Folder 317-333)
  - Bonds, 1961-1963 (Box 9, Folder 334)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1963, 1976-1978 (Box 9, Folder 335-346)
  - Financial Reports, 1956-1958 (Box 9, Folder 347-350)
  - Financial reports, 1961, 1971, 1978-1979 (Box 10, Folder 351-353)
  - Machinists Club, 1958, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 354)
  - Monthly review statements, 1976-1977 (Box 10, Folder 355-356)
- Series IV: Membership Material, 1957-1980
  - Check off lists, 1960-1961, 1966, 1976-1979 (Box 11, Folder 357-361)
  - Dropped list, 1960 (Box 11, Folder 362)
  - Membership Committee minutes and applications, 1957, 1962-1965 (Box 11, Folder 363-364)
  - Per capita payments, 1975-1980 (Box 11, Folder 365-366)
  - Union dues: Meriden Plant, 1960 (Box 11, Folder 367)
  - Membership reports, 1958-1961, 1975-1976 (Box 11, Folder 368-374)
  - Membership reports, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 375-379)
- Series V: Employee Information, undated, 1962-1980
  - Subseries A: General Employee Information, undated, 1962-1979
    - Absentee record, 1972 (Box 13, Folder 380)
    - Configurations from E.S.R., 1978-1979 (Box 13, Folder 381)
    - Employee Distribution, undated (Box 13, Folder 382)
    - Lay offs, 1962-1964, 1970-1971 (Box 13, Folder 383-386)
    - Seniority areas, 1964-1968 (Box 13, Folder 387)
    - Transfers, 1967-1968 (Box 13, Folder 388)
    - Wage data, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 389)
  - Subseries B: Employee Service Records, [Partially Restricted], 1964-1980
    - 1964-1972 (Box 14, Folder 390-398)
    - 1973-1980 (Box 15, Folder 399-406)
- Series VI: Job Descriptions, circa 1952-1980
  - Correspondence, 1970-1977 (Box 16, Folder 407-412)
  - Job evaluations, 1967-1972 (Box 16, Folder 413-416)
  - Job presentations, 1975-1980 (Box 16, Folder 417-418)
  - Occupational group changes, 1970-1974 (Box 16, Folder 419)
  - Seniority Lists, 1965-1968 (Box 16, Folder 420)
  - Job descriptions, circa 1952-1965 (Box 17, Folder 421)
- Series VII: Printed Material and Memorabilia, undated, 1955-1980
  - Subseries A: Printed Material, undated, 1955-1980
    - AFL-CIO
      - COPE, undated (Box 18, Folder 422)
      - Industrial Union Department, undated (Box 18, Folder 423)
      - Metal Trades-Building and Construction Trades, undated (Box 1, Folder 424)
    - American Arbitration Association, undated (Box 18, Folder 425)
    - Coalition for a Just Society, undated (Box 18, Folder 426)
    - IAMAW Grand Lodge
      - Contract Analysis Manual, 1959 (Box 18, Folder 427)
      - 1976 Convention (Box 18, Folder 428-432)
      - Education Bulletin, 1961, 1968 (Box 18, Folder 433)
      - Executive Council minutes, 1960-1977 (Box 18, Folder 434-435)
      - General Publications, undated (Box 18, Folder 436-438)
      - Guide for IAM Newsletters, 1962, 1966-1968 (Box 18, Folder 439)
      - Legislative, undated (Box 18, Folder 440)
      - IAMAW Missile-Aire, 1966-1967 (Box 18, Folder 441-442)
    - IAMAW Lodge 1746
      - Affiliated lodges: general publications, undated (Box 18, Folder 443)
      - Building dedication, 1955 (Box 18, Folder 444)
      - Bylaws, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 445)
      - General publications, undated (Box 18, Folder 446)
      - "In-Sight", undated, 1963 (Box 18, Folder 447)
      - "Lodge 1746 Newspaper", 1948 (Box 18, Folder 448)
      - Stewards newsletter, undated (Box 18, Folder 449)
    - Kiefer, Lou, "Labor Looks Ahead", 1979 (Box 18, Folder 450)
    - Labor News, 1966-1967 (Box 18, Folder 451-452)
    - Machinists Non-Partisan Political League
      - General publications, undated (Box 18, Folder 453)
      - Pamphlets and reports, undated (Box 18, Folder 454)
    - New Union News, 1968-1971 (Box 18, Folder 455)
    - Newspaper articles: general labor issues, 1961-1979 (Box 18, Folder 456)
    - Power Plant, 1966 (Box 18, Folder 457)
    - United Aircraft Corporation, undated (Box 18, Folder 458)
    - United Auto Workers, undated (Box 18, Folder 459)
    - United Technologies Corporation, undated (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - IAMAW Lodge 1746: flyers, 1959-1980 (Box 19, Folder 461-477)
  - Subseries B: Memorabilia, undated
    - Buttons and ribbons (1 envelope), undated (Box 19, Folder 478)
    - General, undated (Box 19, Folder 479-480)